Laura Splan Riot Grrrl Collection, 1992-2011 (Bulk 1994-2005) MSS.423
Fales Library and Special Collections
Laura Splan Riot Grrrl Collection
1992-2011
1994-2005
Fales Library and Special Collections
Splan, Laura
MSS.423
1.5 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes and 1 small oversize box
Laura Splan is an artist who has produced artwork and zines that explore scientific and medical imagery from a feminist perspective. The collection comprises art and zines created by Splan, documentation from events she attended, and zines made by others that she collected.
Biographical Note
Laura Splan attended the University of California, Irvine where she received a Bachelor of Art in 1995. While there, Splan created a number of feminist art projects that examined cultural ambivalence towards the human body, including the zine "I Love My Pussy". She also collaborated with painter and poet Allyson Shaw on video and art projects, including the zine "Beehive", which evolved into a web publication in 1997. "Beehive" featured work by fellow UCI art students including Lala Endara, De Kwok, Lisa Kirk, and Tammy Rae Carland.
Splan's conceptual craft sculptures were included in exhibits at Ladyfest Olympia (2000) and Ladyfest Los Angeles (2002). In 2002 she received a Master of Fine Arts from Mills College in Oakland, California. She currently lives and works in Brooklyn, New York. Her art practice continues to interrogate intersections of Art, Science and Technology. Her work has been exhibited widely at such venues as the Museum of Art & Design (New York, NY), the International Museum of Surgical Science (Chicago, IL), and the Museum of Contemporary Craft (Portland, OR). She has been a visiting artist, lecturer and panelist at Stanford University and the Elizabeth A. Sackler Center for Feminist Art at the Brooklyn Museum, among others.
Scope and Content
The Laura Splan Riot Grrl Collection is comprised of art and zines created by Laura, documentation from Ladyfest 2000 and Ladyfest Bay Area, and zines made by others that she collected.
Series I: Works by Laura Splan consists of art and zines Laura Splan created along with documents of her exhibits and attended events.
Series II: Zines and Comics consists of zines collected by Laura Splan.
OVERSIZE: Series I: Works by Laura Splan contains larger materials of Laura Splan's artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically within each of the two individual series.
Provenance
The collection was donated to NYU's Fales Library & Special Collections by Laura Splan in 2015.
Related Materials
Tammy Rae Carland "I (heart) Amy Carter" Riot Grrrl Collection (MSS.290)
Tammy Rae Carland Riot Grrrl Zine Collection (MSS.320)
Teresa Carmody Ladyfest 2000 Collection (MSS.389)
Ladyfest 2000 Collection (MSS.360)
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Punk culture.; Riot grrrl movement.; Feminism; Correspondence.; Feminism and art.; Photographs.; Comic books.; Zines; Fanzines.; Splan, Laura; Ladyfest; Carland, Tammy Rae, 1965-
- Series I: Works by Laura Splan, 1995-2010
  Scope and Content
  Series I: Works by Laura Splan consists of zines, photography, and slides related to materials created by Laura Splan as well as documentation of her exhibits and attended events.
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged alphabetically because no original order exists.
  - Alternative Communication Exposition All Access Pass, January 12-14, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Booklet: Fuzzy Logic, February 5, 2010-March 13, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Booklet: Laura Splan Sympathetic Coordination, May 4-July 20, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ladyfest 2000 Art Show: Photographic Material (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ladyfest Bay Arena 2002 San Francisco, July 24-28, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ladyfest Bay Area Visual Arts Program, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ladyfest Los Angeles 2002, November 8-11, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter from LaLa (Felix), October 23, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Slides of Art and Photography, 1995-2005 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Woman Dram Drag?" Photographs [1 of 4] with Documentation, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Woman Dram Drag?" Photographs [2 of 4], 1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Woman Dram Drag?" Photographs [3 of 4], 1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Woman Dram Drag?" Photographs [4 of 4], 1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Zines: "Beehive" Master, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Zines: "Beehive" #2 Paste-Up Master, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Zines: "I Love My Pussy" Master [cover missing], undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Zines: "I Love My Pussy" Submissions, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: Zines and Comics, 1992-2011; 1994-2000
  Series II: Zines and Comics consists of zines and comics collected by Laura Splan.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by title of the zine.
  - 949 Market, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Abrasive Agents, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Animal Rights. Abortion Rights. The Politics of Their Co-Existence., undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Big Miss Moviola, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bitch vol. 1 no. 5, Spring 1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bitch no. 11, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bite Size #1, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Blue Hole #2, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chica Loca #1, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Chica Loca #2, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Chica Loca #3, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Chica Loca #5, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Chop Suey Spex #1, February 1, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Chop Suey Spex #2, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Crash Pad, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - The Daughters of Houdini Medical Zine, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Dirty Plotte #11, September 1997 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Don't Call Me Oriental Cuz I'm Chinese Call Me Oriental Cuz I Lie Like a Rug, November 1997 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Femme Flicke #5, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Femme Flicke #6, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Femme Flicke #7, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - From Here On Out, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Girl on the Verge, June 1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Gumption, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Happy Ball, September 4, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hello Friends Quail Season No. 6, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - I Heart Amy Carter #1, December 5, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - I Heart Amy Carter #2, March 15, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - I Heart Amy Carter #3, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Illustrated Woman: The Scond Annual Feminist Activism and Art Conference, February 4-5, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Inkling #3, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Kitchen Sink vol. 4 no. 1, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Madamesoille Menstruelle: My Bloody Sister #2, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Man I Feel Like a Woman, Spring 2005 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Milky #1, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - MIlky #4, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Milky #5, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Milky #6, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Milky #7, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Milky World #3, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - My Last Nerve #2, March 1995 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - My Straight-Faced Twin #1 [with letter insert], undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - My Straight-Faced Twin [with letter insert], undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Queenie #1, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Real Gurls Are Better Than Barbies, Summer 1994 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Signs Journal of Women in Culture and Society vol. 36 no. 2, Winter 2011 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Sock Monkey Social Life #5, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Sock Monkey Social Life #6, January 2004 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Some City Folk, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Tom Girl, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 32)